Guide to the Holy Trinity Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1905-1993 AIS.1993.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Holy Trinity Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1905-1993
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Holy Trinity Serbian Orthodox Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1993.09
3 microfilm_reels (2324 frames)
Holy Trinity Serbian Orthodox Church of Pittsburgh, Pa. was formed in 1961 by the consolidation of St. George Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church of Pittsburgh and the St. Sava Serbian Orthodox Church School Parish of Pittsburgh. The collection contains the birth, baptism,marriage, and death records of both churches as well as Holy Trinity Cathedral, the records span the years 1905-1971. Records through 1954 are in Serbian. Records from 1955-1993 are in English.
History
Holy Trinity Serbian Orthodox Church of Pittsburgh, Pa. was formed in 1961 by the consolidation of St. George Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church of Pittsburgh and the St. Sava Serbian Orthodox Church School Parish of Pittsburgh.
St. George Serbian Orthodox Church was organized in a meeting on October 8, 1905 and the church was incorporated on January 19, 1906 with a first structure on South 25th Street in Pittsburgh's South Side. St. Sava Serbian Orthodox Church was incorporated on August 4, 1935 and was located at 21st and Sidney streets in the South Side of Pittsburgh. Construction of Holy Trinity began in 1969 with dedication, consecration and the first Divine Liturgy service taking place on April 4, 1971. The church has been called the "Holy Trinity Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church-School Congregation of Pittsburgh" and the "Holy Trinity Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church."
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains five series. Series I contains the birth, baptism, and death records of the Serbian-American Parish, 1903, before a church was built. Series II contains the baptism, marriage, and death records of St. George Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church, 1905-1971. Series III contains the birth, baptism, marriage, and death records of the St. Sava Serb Orthodox Church, 1936-1972. Series IV contains the baptism records of St. George Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church, 1938-1973. Series V contains the baptism, marriage, and death records of the Holy Trinity Cathedral.
Note: Records through 1954 are in Serbian. Records from 1955-1993 are in English.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were a gift from Holy Trinity Serbian Orthodox Church, 4920 Clairton Blvd., Pittsburgh, PA. 15236 1993.
Existence and Location of Originals
This collection has been microfilmed by Archives of Industrial Society and the Western Pennsylvania Genealogical Society from originals in the possession of Holy Trinity Serbian Orthodox Church, 4920 Clairton Blvd., Pittsburgh, PA. 15236
Previous Citation
Holy Trinity Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1905-1993, AIS.1993.09, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Holy Trinity Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church, Pittsburgh, PA., Records, 1905-1993, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries.
Church records; South Side (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Church history; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Church history; Serbian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Ethnic groups; Churches and Synagogues; Baptismal records -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Birth records; Death records; Communion records; Marriage records; Srpska pravoslavna crkva. Diocese for the United States of America and Canada; St. George Serbian Orthodox Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); St. Sava Serbian Orthodox Church-School Parish of Pittsburgh (Pa.); Holy Trinity Serbian Orthodox Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Serbian-American Parish Records, 1903; I.
  - Volume 1, 1903 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
- St. George Serbian Eastern Orthodox Church Records, 1905-1971; II.
  - Baptisms, 1905-1906 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Marriages, 1905-1906 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Deaths, 1905-1906 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Baptisms, 1907-1909 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Deaths, 1907-1909 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Marriages, 1907-1910 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Baptisms, 1909-1910 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Baptisms, October 1905 - December 1909 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Marriages, October 1905 - November 1921 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Deaths, October 1905 - April 1914 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Baptisms, November 1909 - March 1913 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Deaths, December 1909 - August 1910 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Baptisms, April 1913 - March 1915 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Deaths, April 1914 - August 1925 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Deaths, 1926-1930 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Baptisms, October 1921 - September 1927 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Baptisms, March 1915 - October 1921 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Marriages, 1922 - February 1971 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Baptisms, October 1927 - May 1937 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Deaths, September 1930 - February 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Record 2)
  - Baptisms, September 1937 - 1939 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
- St. Sava Serb Orthodox Church, 1936-1972; III.
  - Baptisms, 1936-1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Marriages, 1936-1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Record 2)
  - Deaths, 1936-1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Births/Baptisms, 1945-1972 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Marriages, 1945-1972 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Record 2)
  - Deaths, 1946-1972 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
- St. George Serbian Orthodox Church, 1938-1973; IV.
  - Baptisms, December 1938 - April 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Baptisms, 1956 - April 1973 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 3)
- Holy Trinity Cathedral, 1971 - June 1993; V.
  - Baptisms, Marriages, Deaths, 1971 - June 1993 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 3)